all right so welcome to another waiting
for the meeting crisis discord Q&A with
part 2 with Nick B who has been telling
us about the lessons he's learned from
his time in cults and in for cults and
so last week he he took us through sort
of the story and now I think we're going
to get a little more into the what he's
learned from from that time so again
thank you Nick for for being here
absolutely yeah this this part is a
little bit more theoretical and more of
the kind of sense making that I've done
after the fact it's a little bit more
controversial as well if some of the
conversations I've had about this topic
are any indication so yeah let's see the
plan I've got for today is starting with
the etymology of the word kind of how
it's it's popular use that we now think
of it in terms of in terms of came about
because it's actually extremely recent
that we started using the word cult this
way from there I go into what I consider
to be a much more useful framing so a
lot of that is dealing with quite
directly posing an alternative use for
the word and the idea of what a cult is
and what it represents
[Music]
and then from there I go into some
features of cults and I kind of frame
this question rather than what makes
something a cult and what makes it not a
cult I instead try and frame the
question around what makes a good cult
and what makes a bad cult and how do how
does this transition occur and as you'll
see when I get to that part many of the
aspects that we find in cults we we find
you know everywhere within our culture
and our society and even our direct
personal relationships and friendships
and yeah I'll talk more about that
right so starting off I figured I'd go
start off pretty clear-cut here the word
cult really wasn't used very much until
the late 19th century early 20th century
and we see a pretty sharp spike in its
arrived or in its use around 1910 to
1920 this also coincides with the first
Red Scare around 1920 although we
actually see its use coming up from
religious people making Kierkegaard e'en
like critiques about religion so they
Iran eclis enough they they wanted to
call their worship cult it a cult rather
than a religion because they felt that
the word religion had been to neutered
and did not accurately represent any
longer what it meant to be a religious
person had been so soaked up by the
dominant culture that you people
couldn't even tell that they were in a
religion to some degree just because the
it was such a universal belief so yeah
that's where you start seeing our modern
use of it Crump back up the word cult
comes from Latin koltes which means care
labor cultivation culture worship or
reverence and originally tended or
cultivated from the past participle of
Coulier - till right so tilling
preparing something for growth
opening something up right opening this
potential by which something may you
know happen it shares the root the same
root Colo as colony does and colonial
which is probably an interesting tie for
how people talk about to loan
utilization today and interestingly
let's see
yeah so from in in fits word halls
modern English from 1873 we see this
movement of the word cult back into
religious conversation where he says
cult is a turn which as we value
exactness we can ill do without seeing
how completely religion has lost its
original signification and then write
another entry I jokingly put in here but
I think is very relevant for for the
discussion later is cult an organized
group of people religious or not with
whom you disagree and this is from hugh
ross ins wicked words from 1993 which is
obviously written with a strong dose of
irony
so yeah what I want to kind of focus on
here is this transition by which the
word cult picks up its pejorative
meaning and this actually happens
surprisingly later than one would think
you know it's as late as 1977 the
dictionary had no pejorative definition
for the word cult and you know it still
was not defined by what we would now
call a cult so it's it's granted
dictionaries sometimes take a little bit
of time to alter meaningfully words and
how they change it seems pretty clear
that it wasn't until the early to mid
70s or so that the word cult
really started getting this pejorative
connotation and you can actually even
see it like if you look up the news
articles at the time from when man stand
was arrested in his trial very very few
of the articles from that time will
bring up the word cult at all usually
they used the word ritual right
ritualized murders or ritual killings to
describe what happened with the Manson
Family likewise when we look at Lifton's
work who I brought up last time he is
the person that invented the idea of
brainwashing and he created this by
looking at the techniques of the
Communist Chinese the Maoist movement
and and that's where he got the entire
idea of brainwashing so it very clearly
starts as a political tool and we see
this more obviously throughout all of
the 20th century with sudden massive in
influx of propaganda
and it's it's you know extreme use by
you know various political movements and
then when you get to the 60s and the
kind of free love movement and this
sudden influx of what we're called new
religious movements a lot of this being
born from a massive influx of Eastern
philosophy into the Western tradition
that started and around the 20s that
kind of peaked with the beatniks in the
40s and 50s and then started becoming
almost mainstream by the time you get to
the hippies in the 60s basically people
started in the 70s applying this word
cult to understanding how these new
religious movements were functioning and
I actually think that if we were to pin
the moment on when cult got its most
pejorative use it was likely through the
satanic ritual abuse scare from the 80s
so when we think of the word cult
we're probably calling back only as
recently to the 80s where if people
don't know there was a huge mass
hysteria going on at the time of satanic
ritual abuse cults and people you know
like preschool teachers we're getting
you know brought into courts for
paranoid parents believing that they
were performing satanic rituals on their
children it's really interesting if you
look into it it was it was a type of
memetic virus that went through the
culture that seemed to have little
actual bearing on the reality
you know I'm certain that there were as
there always as many people doing very
creepy shit in the background and so one
could likely find examples of people
doing creepy shit from that period but
it was interesting in that it very much
had this type of mass hysterical effect
in mass historical events are also
something I recommend looking into
they're really interesting and there's a
number of examples of them that go back
quite far one infamous one I think from
the Dark Ages being a case where a very
large group of people suddenly started
dancing and could not stop to the point
that the people were dancing themselves
to death
quite literally dying from exhaustion in
the middle of dancing really bizarre
snoring but really interesting to look
into my point here is is that when
people try and make arguments like you
know the word cult has always been used
to form a healthy boundary around what
is acceptable culture and what is not
papers they are either lying or they're
ignorant
and have no understanding of likewise we
actually there's several domains and we
still use the word in a positive context
most notable noticeably in art and
entertainment right when we say
something has a cult following or is a
cult classic it does not carry its usual
pejorative
patient sorry my roommate is being very
loud I can't I can't hear it okay so I
think it's important also to realize
that a lot of this kind of like sudden
fear or of brainwashing that gets tied
to cults is very distinctly a political
one right it's it's distinctly political
and then it gets dragged into religious
and pseudo religious ideologies as time
passes due to the similarities and it's
no coincidence I don't think that we see
a sudden increase in the rise of the
term cult distinctly at periods not
where there was a lot of religious
activity going on but where there was a
lot of political activity going on so
again right liftin writes his work to do
literally as a counter against the
growing communist fear right and and
another well-known cult researcher
Lolich the cult that she was in was
distinctly a political one it had no
religious ties at all it was the
Democratic Workers Party or something
like DWP here in America and it was
after leaving that cult that she became
a cult researcher and started applying
you know what she had learned from her
time in it to a broader sociological
lens
so we have to be pretty aware that that
a lot of this a lot of its use often
comes down to seemingly this attempt
following World War two to try and
totalize a culture when you have rules
and laws like the freedom of speech and
freedom of religious affiliation forget
with the ring right you basically you
start needing a way to control the
Overton Window of your culture
particularly in time very divisive times
like following the World War two and
during the Cold War such that you don't
you're able to properly frame your
country against an enemy without having
the country split apart inside of itself
so yes yes often when we're dealing with
the word cult we're looking at a
political a political tool that got
repurposed for religious and although
all of these ends seem to be very and
primarily concerned with controlling the
Overton Window and this may I've not
actually arguing against using a word of
this way as I was mistaken in the
previous conversation we do need
normalizing terms and we need boundary
condition terms those are both very
useful things but I think it's it's
important for us to remember exactly
what the word is doing and likewise
there comes a point where which I think
we have long since passed now where that
normative function can't actually
survive due to the internal tensions of
the culture that we are in and I
actually lay this quite quite distinctly
at the feet of the meaning crisis so I
would say that one aspect of
meaning crisis and perhaps a postmark
modernity in a more general sense is
that it has a way of fractioning
worldviews and removing the mechanisms
by which we hierarchically ordered
worldviews such that everyone is already
looking at everyone else in our current
cultural situation as in as if they're
in a cult already right so the Atheist
look at the Christians and think they're
in a cult the Christians look at the
atheists and think they're in a cult the
Democrats look at the Republicans and
vice versa
great everyone is already looking at
everyone else by their ideological
identification and then how that
ideological identification doesn't just
stay as a ideology or a worldview inside
that person's head but how it scales in
the sociological systems that the person
belongs to I would also say that part of
what's driven our kind of conception in
that direction is the massive rise of
branding through the 20th century and
again if you think what the word is
right a brand is what a farmer would put
on his animals so that people knew who
the animal belonged to and I don't think
it's a mistake that we use the word
brand to describe the clothing we wear
or how we walk around as literal free
advertising space for companies and I
think it's really important to kind of
get a phenomenological understanding of
what exactly is occurring when we wear a
giant logo on our chest and then go out
into the world and interact with others
presenting ourselves in the armor of
this larger symbol that represents a
cultural affiliation that we hope so
radii I think it's important one to kind
of look at it from the perspective of
why are we doing that like what's our
take
when I put on a piece of branded
clothing or whatever a bumper sticker on
my car what I'm communicating to myself
right so its ability to hold and form my
internal sense of identity and then on
the secondary how we do this in a
projective way so that we can use them
as heuristics for navigating social
space right so when someone's wearing a
whatever a Volcom t-shirt you know we
know they're probably some type of
skateboarder or surfer or you know
somewhere in that culture that they
probably have some you can get a hint of
the musical taste they probably like
from Punk but rock you know whatever
little range of things you know how what
they're probably going to talk like you
know right you're able to identify in a
group of strangers who you will most
likely be able to have a fun
conversation with through the use of
branding so in many ways I would I would
view branding as a very distinct but a
very weak form of cultic affiliations
and I think that this really starts to
reach its peak when you see for instance
you know it was a couple years ago
Facebook was going I don't know if they
did it or not but they were going to
launch a relationship I kind of like you
know tinder or whatever maybe something
less overtly sexual than tinder but a
relationship mapping matching service
through Facebook and the main mechanism
that they used to decide I mean this was
actually fairly genius both from an
advertising standpoint and because it
probably would have worked what they
used as the metric for if two people
would get along was the
branded the brand pages that the person
followed on Facebook so they kind of
double I double doubled the incentive
here one as they made it so that people
using the service would make sure to
comb through all their favorite brand
pages and like them which made
advertising to the people easier with
targeted ads through Facebook and
likewise it it allowed them to have
better matches by looking at the range
of cultic affiliations that the person
subscribed to and thus was able to match
people across various groups based on
their ideologies as communicated by
whether they liked the supreme or not so
one can get a pretty distinct sense here
of how dystopic this type of thing can
can be when it is unconscious and used
against us and also how extremely useful
and I would argue fundamental it is to
our ability to train our heuristics in a
society where you don't have a clear
unified culture yeah
I'll take a quick break there before
diving further into this and see if
anyone has any questions what was a
really good job Nick
I was just gonna make a comment that was
really good thank you so I was wondering
so you made the point that that the term
cult almost has a propagandist tint to
it where the people didn't like these
groups were using it for ative lee to
brand them but you think we're sort of
stuck with that negative that negative
connotation to the word now kind of
again there are uses of it that are less
pejorative although it's contextually
based more so than anything the
mechanism that I've kind of gone for is
not to actually appropriate the word
cult itself although I do think that we
need to be a little bit more comfortable
with it particularly how it's being used
now within our our culture what the the
method I've gone is rather to focus to
turn it into an adjective rather than a
noun so when I'm trying to talk about
the frame that I'm trying to communicate
here I'll point out the cultic nature of
something right I'll say cultic
structures or cultic affiliations rather
than trying to stick the noun form on
somebody and the point of that is to get
them to kind of see the mechanisms by
which their Association associative
system is working right it's not
functioning on on the set of tools of
like rational you know choice freewill
based mechanisms it's largely based on
these subconscious belief structures and
heuristic systems that are embedded in
our cognition and and the point of using
it also to use the word cultic as
opposed to another word is to try and
get the person to break frame a little
bit right so I wanna I want to make use
of that negative connotation but I want
to make use of it in a way that it
reveals something to the person not
punches them in the face with with you
know an imagined insult so yeah that's
that's part of the argument for why I've
gone about it this way it is in some
sense to use purvey keys term a reinvent
EO although I don't actually think it's
so much a reinvent EO as it is properly
criticizing poor research in in the
realms in which this has been studied
which I'll get into and trying to be a
bit more honest and then from there to
be able to recover tools that I deeply
believe it's not even believed that seem
absolutely unavoidable within human
social systems and to be able to
consciously recover them and and frame
it in such a way that we can see more
clearly how things we need can be very
bad for us what one example I use quite
a lot because they think it's it's
actually really accurate almost a
one-to-one mapping is is the word
relationship right and and so
relationships whether friendships or or
you know mating whatever deeper
relationships are some of the most
abject ly dangerous things a human being
will ever encounter rate and the the
potential for them to be enormous ly
damaging to the point of ruining a
person's life or even causing death
never mind abuse right the potential for
all this this horrible slew of things is
absolutely present in relationship
but when we go to study relationships we
not we do not do it by demonizing
relationships and then trying to go you
know ask the question of how do I relate
to you without ever being in
relationship with you right instead what
we go what we do is we go okay
relationships are dangerous and there's
healthy forms of relationship and
there's unhealthy forms of relationship
and there's many mechanisms within that
where the the parts that make the
relationship meaningful are also the
thing that makes it dangerous and so
what it's allowed is a really robust
study to come out where we're able to
look at how these little bits happening
these these largely subconscious and you
know very detailed aspects play
themselves out and we're able to more
meaningfully categorize what a negative
or a unhealthy relationship is and how
one can work within the relationship and
with a relationship to put it on a
course toward something better and I
think that is the same mechanism or the
same the same lens we need to take when
we talk about cults and cultic
structures and I think it would actually
enable a much more robust study of our
sociological systems and how those
sociological systems interact with our
phenomenological reality so the four
cults that you were a part of would you
characterize them as unhealthy cults yes
yes absolutely but again it's not as cut
and dry as I would like to be able to
make it so I brought this up in that
first one with the Harry Krishna's it's
like me is a relatively healthy normal
outsider coming in would go oh this is
unhealthy but when I look at its ability
to take people that would definitely be
living on the street or would have died
from a drug overdose or you know
anything else like it did wonderful
things for those
people and they were living much better
lives than they would have in any other
circumstance so it's hard for me to just
blank it give a blanket definition and
say that was bullshit and all those
people were being abused no was there a
spate of abuse going on yes do you think
all the people running those cults saw
themselves as being good cults or do you
think they knew something was off I I
would say in all of the ones that I
interacted with they absolutely thought
that they were doing something good
none of them none of the actors that I
interacted with excepting cult 4
although hope for is really hard to get
a grip on because they inverted almost
every expectation and and system for
navigating these spaces that you could
imagine so I'd have to spend a lot more
time figuring out what was going on or
communicating what was going on there in
the first three absolutely these people
did not think and they had the noblest
of intentions and in many cases they
were able to successfully deliver on
those noble intentions and and a lot of
it you know the funkiness came in from
from the necessary faults of being a
person and letting selfish desires
slide in
but they were not objectively
manipulative they were not trying to
manipulate again that you know aware of
what they were doing I mean and this is
common you know Jones from Jones town
you know he kills himself with everyone
else right right yeah did that answer
the question yeah and I guess III think
you may be coming to this but then so
the the question the next question is
therefore you know how do we how do we
we have good intentions here how do we
avoid becoming dubbing the bad cult
right right and I I will get I will get
into this where we yeah we got plenty of
time I should be good on time this time
any other questions at this stage
all right I do it's just I've been
taking notes so there's just so much
here and I really appreciate you going
through us because it's a lot in terms
of using the word and the definition
changing over time do you see the
definition changing again perhaps back
to a more positive outlook yes and I
think that this will largely come likely
from when people finally realize that
rather than defending themselves from
the endless you know everyone calling
each other the cult when they just give
up trying to defend and say my things
nautical your thing is a cult and they
just go sure whatever it's a cult
and when that happens I think it will in
a very post ironic sense actually start
to recover its its definition I would
hope that by the time something like
that happens there is actually some
robust understanding of the mechanisms
at play because I think that could slide
into hellish territory very quickly
thank you yeah I'm breaking the boundary
to try and put up a better wall rather
than breaking the boundary just to go
look it's all the same
all right let me get to my layout and
see where I am
so okay yeah let's go over two of the
more common modern definitions of the
word cult one is from Lolich and i
forget where the other one was from but
I'm pretty sure I read it in Daniel
Shaw's traumatic narcissism which is I I
haven't read much of Locke's work but I
have read most of Daniel Shaw's
traumatic narcissism it's a very useful
book I recommend it I'll get into this
later but I think it is actually way
more useful to teach people about
traumatic narcissism and to frame what
we often complain about in cults or view
as dangerous not in terms of cults but
in terms of dealing with narcissistic
personality disorder one because it
reminds you of just how extraordinarily
present narcissism is it gives you tools
for dealing with it in any circumstance
in which you may see it arise whether
it's in a group setting or at a direct
interpersonal setting and I think it it
has a much better analysis than the work
done on cults so far so that's that's a
recommended reading from me he was also
in a cult a hidden do cult which is an
interesting side topic
yeah so starting with Lex definition and
we'll really be able to see how this
falls apart at least I think sorry I'm
trying to find where I've written the
definition
oh you know what I did not copy and
paste it into this box sorry give me
just a second
right so we'll play with two definitions
one is from right here off of Lex
website hope research a cult can be
either a sharply bounded social group or
a diffusely bounded social movement held
together through shared commitment to a
charismatic leader it upholds a
transcendent belief system often but not
always religious in nature that includes
a call for a personal transformation
it also requires I high level of
personal commitment from its members in
words or entities this definition is not
meant to be evaluative in the sense of
implying that a group is good bad benign
or harmful right there we see it lose
its normative function rather it is
meant to convey a systemic view of such
a group which is comprised of a
charismatic relationship a promise of
fulfillment and the methodology by which
to achieve cults differ in their
specific ruling ideologies and in their
specific requirements practices and
behaviors a single group may even differ
over its lifetime or across different
locations these groups exist on a
continuum of influence regarding a
particular groups effect on its members
and on society vice-versa and a
continuum of control from less invasive
to all-encompassing coast can be
distinct distinguished from other non
mainstream groups for example religious
or political segments fringe or
alternative groups or movements communes
and intentional communities because of
their intense ideologies and their
demand for total commitment from at
least some of the members
that paragraph alone should have thrown
up a few questionable flags each group
must be observed and judged on its own
merits and its practices and behaviors
as to whether it falls within this
category type which is not meant to be
dismissive or one-sided
quotes are frequently totalistic and
separatist some cults are total istic
when they are exclusive in their
ideology and impose upon their members
systems of social control that are
confining and all-inclusive some culture
separatists when they promote withdrawal
from the larger society now that last
one actually that last little bit I
actually found useful because I think
adding an adjective in front of the word
cults is probably the most useful way to
go about it so write describing what
type of cultic structure it is right is
it totalistic is it authoritarian is it
narcissistic some mixture of these but
as hopefully you could you could pick up
on on reading that one her definition
slips multiple times so the way she
defines it at one point runs counter to
the way she defines it later and the
other problem actually comes up when I
did a little further research on her
definition of charismatic and her
definition of charismatic actually has
nothing at all to do with a charismatic
leader rather she defines charisma as a
response in the recipient such that a
leader is a charismatic leader so long
as someone finds him to be charismatic
now you can see why she made this move
because one the move away from
essentialism is very popular nowadays
and two because essentialism in this
case being that the leader has some
quality that makes him cares man
and to because you have to deal with the
very real problem that right certain
figures that some find charismatic
others find actively repelling and so
you need some way to figure out what
exactly the word charisma is supposed to
be pointing to my contention would be
that within a secular context the word
charisma means absolutely nothing if you
look into the etymology of the word
charisma it comes straight out of
Christianity in the form of terrorism
the plural plural of which was Cara's
Matta and literally means a gift from
God so the person has some gift given to
them by God that makes them very
proficient beyond the level of normal
human achievement in a secular context
all it means is that a person is able to
convince somebody else of something and
I think that's probably a more useful
way to go about it than trying to deal
with the word charisma within the
context these people are using it so
right and I think we can also have much
stronger mechanisms by which we can
define how a person may be convincing
and it helps us move away from the naive
assumption that a cult leader has to act
like Tony Robbins in order to be very
effective at what he does I would argue
right a person can be deeply not
charismatic in the traditional sense of
the word and can still form a very
strong following only because they make
very convincing arguments for example
yeah
so so there's that's a major problem
with this is that when when you define
what a cult is based on what someone who
listens to it responds you end up in the
situation where anyone can rightfully
call anything a cult so long as they can
find some person that treats it as if it
is one the other problem is that the
definition they give is so mushy
in one sense that it becomes really hard
to not describe many totally normal
social systems as cults
despite their really weak attempt here
to to separate them by just saying it's
not an intentional community because an
intentional communities called Lehman in
an intentional community and it's not
called a cult I should also point out
cult number two that I came across
cinder land the one that was building an
ark to sail to Machu Picchu upon the
ocean rise from global warming it was an
intentional community specifically an
eco village and was not at all a cult
and was at the time I was there lacking
its charismatic leader so I guess it was
not a cult by this definition which is
the other problem with this definition
is that it fails to recognize that many
of the qualities that we most that are
most dangerous about cults have
absolutely nothing to do with the
specific qualities that they pointed out
in this definition so right many very
deeply manipulative groups exist that do
not have a clear single leader that acts
as a lightning rod for the group you can
see extreme systems of subjugation and
abuse within a system where people are
not obviously lined up behind
and instead you can see it largely
waited on a distinctly bureaucratic
system and in many ways this gets into
the the work of Ghent which Emmanuel
Ghent which I brought up last time in
his difference between surrender I think
I brought it up last time surrender and
subjugation he makes the point that
subjugation as a deeply dehumanizing
element to it and I would argue that
bureaucracies are actually far more
efficient at at dehumanizing large
swathes of people and doing so in a way
that it doesn't immediately set off our
red flags like it often does in cultic
settings where you have a clear speaker
box so my biggest criticism here is that
one this definition is not very strong
it kind of suffers from two main
problems one it overly scales and two it
underly scales so it does it in weird
dimensions such that it's losing a lot
of its actual use as a term and I think
that this is in some sense deeply
fundamental to the problem of
meaningfully defining what a cult is in
in these very limited terms or limited
scope which is that you end up doing
quite a tremendous amount of nonsensical
rationalizing in order to describe
normal healthy sociological systems as
not cults and likewise describing really
damaging bureaucratic systems as cults
you'll end up tearing your own
definition apart in the effort to fit it
within the category in that way
cool yeah so that was a bit of a rant
one of the stronger arguments that I
came across and again I think this was
from Shaw this this more leans on the on
the argument that a cult is necessarily
authoritarian and the way he defined it
is that within a cultic structure the
highest authority within that structure
has no higher authority above them or
otherwise lacks some mechanism of checks
and balances so by that definition right
Hitler and Nazi Germany was a cult
leader kim jeong-hoon or ill hoon and
then ill our cult leaders because they
do not have a higher legal authority and
neither do they have meaningful checks
and balances systems within their
government to rein in their power if it
starts going out of control arguably
this is the main critique of Western
countries over communism is that it is
fundamentally cultic because it loses
the mechanism to rein in the
authoritarian spouts work once he has
been granted it for the sake of
restructuring society
and I think that this is arguably a a
much stronger way to define what a
cultic system is than Alec's
work here however I think it's it
likewise suffers from from some problems
in that again just because a system has
checks and balances or has a right a
group of people that are able to debate
with each other at the highest level of
its authority does not actually mean
that the system is going to not produce
the exact same types of authoritarian
structures it just can do so through
different mechanisms in my framing I
would argue that a system with really
distinct checks and balances is part of
what makes a healthy cult as opposed to
is what makes something not a cult and
again I I make that move to try and
recognize that checks and balances in
and of themselves are not enough to make
sure that a system remains healthy or
non non abusive to its members so that's
probably the most contentious part of
what I'm going to say here going through
the definitions and redefining through
this system so this is probably a good
spot again to stop and ask if there's
any questions or any people that would
like to push back or wonder it why I'm
making the moves I'm making
I have a question please um the question
is does the court of King Arthur oh the
archetypical wise King
laughs I as a cult and is in some sense
the notion of a cult and up with that
which is pernicious as opposed to that
which is isin in release salutary even
if it corresponds to all the same can
exceed blade out I mean it certainly has
the connotation I think it would be
tremendously useful to if not be able to
recover the word in a meaningful way to
at least recover it as a description of
our social sociology sociology and in
the later half here I want to get more
into what these elements are that make
up these cultic structures how they're
healthy useful right in the case of the
wise King if you will or can be and how
those same aspects can be used against
us for the sake of manipulation or for
the satisfaction of some persons you
know narcissistic impulse kind of like a
technology dual use which be salutary
into abuse right
as much
I think I get what I think I get the
gist of how you're redefining it but I
also wonder is there some utility in
keeping the definition to sort of these
small smallish groups with a
quote-unquote charismatic leader who I
know I mean I see charismatic is more
than just you can convince anyone but
sort of somebody with a particular gift
of the gab who doesn't have to have
great arguments or whatnot to convince
people it's just through force of
personality and and that they're and
that they have sort of almost a
mesmerizing type of hold on on their
people that seems to be a utility in
having a word that describes that type
of group rather than a definition that
could include governments you know you
know of entire countries that that so
Lolich is i by their own definition the
definition that you just gave of cults
is not in any way the definition of
cults they explicitly called North Korea
a cult they make it very clear that
there is not in any way a limit on size
as to what constitutes a cult and what
does not so we could create or redefine
the word cult from a scholarly
standpoint to distinctly talk about
groups of less than a thousand people or
or 500 again it just starts to become
really arbitrary so yeah likewise I
would say that the gift of the gab or
say like what's often contained in the
word sophist right a person that can
make an argument convincing based on the
force of their personality rather than
on the efficacy of the argument the way
I've dealt with this is again making
perhaps a similar type of move that I'm
making right now which is that people
can be convinced on using any number of
channels the interpersonal channel is
definitely one that can be
use of and abused to convince something
or someone of something regardless of
whether it's a good argument or not so I
agree that there is definitely utility
in making sure we are deeply aware of
that type of ability to convince it
maybe even totally appropriate to title
it with the term charisma my point is
more that when we are speaking about
these cultic groups if we define it only
in terms of charisma you're gonna miss a
huge swathe of deeply abusive systems of
subjugation that are not built around a
classically charismatic leader
there's other ways to fudge people's
circuits so that they become convinced
other than the interpersonal one and if
you make use of those and abuse them
then you can still create these abusive
systems and get to say oh it's not a
cult though because I don't you know I
don't stand up straight enough for it to
be cultural cult or whatever right you
know putting on the air of social
authority any other questions for Nick
on this section a very quick follow-up
question if I can Nick
a matter of degree in some sense a cult
following is to imply a kind of a
further cult seemed to imply a fervor
which is in relation to the perceived
charisma or the kind of power of the
belief system you see something
something which otherwise might be seen
as a cult doesn't actually amps with the
definition because people like yeah I'd
leave this tomorrow if it didn't work
out or for me I wouldn't it's like
something about impeach ability of the
leader the view and the fervor and
compassion with which with with which
it's the feud which is one of the kind
of like taxonomic criteria which says
yeah this is a cult right although what
I would be so I think there's two
potential ways to error by by defining
it that way
one is is a hypo and one is hyper so one
you have the problem then that the only
way for you to be not cultic is to not
give a shit about anything that you do
in your life right so that's like the
coolness right you should never be
excited or believe strongly in something
that you're doing and that's how you
avoid ever enter being called a cult
member now well there's probably some
wisdom to that right we should have some
amount of restraint to how we interact
with the system's it can also I think
lead towards a nihilistic world view
where coolness is the highest factor and
that's my ability to be dis
passionate becomes defined as what makes
me a worthy or worthwhile person so that
would be one negative potential I see
from defining it in such a way the other
is in the fact that if we define it in
that way than anyone excited about
anything we could call then we could say
that there then belonging to a cult I
don't say I'm not saying it's a
sufficient condition I'm saying it's a
necessary condition oh I'm not saying
hey if you're if you're enthusiastic
here in some kind of cult ciao
oh I'm just saying like it'd be
difficult to find a group of people who
were like disinclined to like really
defended you
Confederate around the view - right
Federer around the leader and saying you
guys were in a cult they'd be like what
just a friend he just knows these
mountains best so we follow him because
he's already have a fuckin thing right
yeah that's that's that's fair and I
don't have anything distinctly against
that again
I might make arguments where it's like
in some sense you don't even need to
deeply be Confederated around an
ideology in order for many of the
aspects of cultic systems to be at play
so it can be just very close friendships
with with a group of people or something
along those lines so there's I think
you're I think you're making a good
point there and then it may be that we
need another type of lens to view with
how those other interpersonal sub mostly
subconscious effects still have an
impact on us Brett would you mute please
oh sorry sorry I thought it was again
Nick that was it thank you
nikka I kind of missed that because
Brett was speaking would you mind
repeating your answer you said um that
you thought he was making another good
point in that we need another type of
lens right I was saying insofar as is
that is a good point which I I'm
definitely willing to concede there's
something to what he's saying there I
think what can we would in order to hold
that point up strongly and still have a
robust lens for understanding how social
effects can take place outside of
ideological social structures so just in
the case of being part of a group of
friends that aren't United around
perhaps any activity fervor with fervor
how we can still heavily be kind of put
at the whim at how that social group
operates so if we don't want to use a
cultic lens in that case because it's
not based around an ideology or even a
certain fervor we would need some way to
look at how groups of people can impact
our phenomenology using sociological
systems or tools
I would do so using a cultic lens
because I think it captures a lot of
stuff and gives us a robust lens but I
think if we were to make that that
delineation we would need some other
kind of little tool set to deal with in
those those other environments just kind
of step away for a minute but please
keep on talking and I just have some
children issues sorry I thought I was
needed before but I'll I'll be back so
I'm listening but so keep on going
anyone else or should I continue I have
a quick question well perhaps not quick
but maybe um just for times sake
so you said what makes a healthy cult
potentially as checks-and-balances yet
you said it's it's not enough for a
system to remain healthy not abusive so
what part of checks and balances is good
enough and what part of it is not good
enough well I would say that checks and
balances offer a security mechanism
right they they have a corrective
mechanism that would otherwise be
missing however just because that
corrective mechanism exists does not
mean that there doesn't mean that it's
correcting along the correct path if you
will I would say that it also has sort
of a prophylactic property to it as well
because if those systems are in place
actors within the system will tend to
behave differently now right we're at
Lee right being for a time a different
way yes although what it can also allow
much sneakier forms of manipulation
because people think they're in a system
with checks and balances and those
checks and balances are not operating
according to the rules but they think
they're operating according to
right so this might be something like
paying out you know classic forms of
corruption in systems that have checks
and balances of the blue check box and
there's an exam right nice check and
balance system but right yeah yeah in
some sense checks and balances allow us
some level of correction and that's part
of what offers a health to a system but
it does not ensure it is my only point
there thank you I think maybe a good
example would be like your unions
because immune system can't afford to
keep everything out because it will need
to eat there's still a defense mechanism
against things and fuel not have your
best interests at heart let's say right
and there's two categories of error
there one where it's overly attacking
things foreign things coming in and then
the other where it starts attacking
itself in in that effort right so you've
got to be able to judge the near
response so it's not to various but it's
also not inert you're just trying to
maintain homeostasis we're down to is
keeping the system balanced and not
destroying others or destroying itself
has no food right right
yeah and there's of course many yeah
perceptual problems that come yeah and a
lot of my argument here is like you're
never gonna design the right system
right it's like if we could in the sense
of like Plato's Republic or something
right we would all be living in the the
wonderful perfect utopia and we would
have been here from you know a hundred
thousand years ago you know we've had a
lot of of our greatest minds try and
tackle these problems none of them have
ever been able to design a system that
was free from these issues
well can I jump in there again sorry I
just wanted to say that's very much in
line with us keys hope I think it was
toski but his halting problems because
he showed basically that there's no way
to design an algorithm so that the
algorithm itself will report if the
algorithm has failed but you can't you
can't trust the system to report to fade
that you have to investigate it
independently and write that that's just
like that that basic limitation applies
to to any kind of system you want to
build doesn't matter what it is and so
no matter what you design it will always
have that flaw within it thing was
touring yeah sorry Turing is probably
right that didn't sound right to me when
I said to ask you sir
Thanks yes yeah that's that's a great
example and I make an argument about
this later when I get into that kind of
health and unhealth and how an in a very
very real way you know I borrow from
verbe keys ecology of practices here
where it's kind of like you know you
can't design the perfect practice you
can't even design the perfect like list
of practices instead it's by following
the practices in this ecological kind of
balance
and in this very dynamic sense that you
can in some way get a grasp on the
corrections in between your practices
and even and obviously that's not an
insured path to success but I think it
does give us a vision of just how very
serious the problem of bullshitting is
and then allows us to move forward being
conscious of that propensity and trying
to correct for it
anyone else sir shall I keep going ma'am
my throat is acting up a little earlier
than last time
all right we've burnt through quite a
bit of time so I might actually just go
ahead I think I've communicated my man I
have a lot of stuff we can do part
communicated I think the lens I'm using
clear enough does any way anyone have
any questions on on the lens I'm using
and why I'm using it just to clarify it
seems like you're trying to look at the
connotations in the history of cult the
word itself and looking at the
mechanisms by which it operates
sociologically right right and then I'm
also trying to make the argument that in
our current meaning crisis-ridden
culture the normative function that was
originally being put to use by the word
cult is breaking down in meaning and
that the way we're using it is that now
actively detrimental instead of useful
and that's where part of the necessity
aspect of my argument is coming from it
should be noted that that both Lolich
and another researcher that makes an
arguments similar to hers
wrote books or think books articles at
least on how Trump is a cult so you know
putting to use its normative function in
this way I'm not sure you know if even
the supposed great cult experts of our
time are using it in this way I'm not
sure that it's use is justified any
longer and that we need a more nuanced
perspective on how to deliver just not
to say that there are not coltie aspects
in it well in all of politics there's
something a little creepy about a cult
expert using it as a political argument
also I'm I'm not trying to make a
political argument here either I'm not a
fan personally
thing I don't think it's adding to the
healthy dialogue of our country to just
call it Trump's whole thing and Colton
be done with it
I think that's because you're in a cult
just know Trump is continued all right
so finally let's get into some of the
problems some of the good examples and
some of the bad examples so I brought up
earlier
Daniel Shaw's book traumatic narcissism
relational systems of subjugation is the
subtitle tomato worth a read take it
with a grain of salt but nonetheless a
lot of valuable information there and I
wanted to tie some of one I wanted to
kind of deal with the extraordinary rise
of narcissism that's currently a major
feature of our culture and how everyone
is in some sense trying their hardest to
become a cult leader except that the
reward for doing so is instead of free
sex with all the women is a lot of likes
on your on your Instagram page and then
more importantly I wanted to focus on so
there's two aspects here one is that I
think what we are picking up on and what
people are picking up on in our current
age as narcissistic power is actually a
bastardization of something that is
truly and deeply powerful and meaningful
and necessary for humans which I've been
terming ontological power and then I
wanted to relate that difference between
ontological and narcissistic power to
the difference between surrender and
Submission which again comes from
Immanuel dense work he's a psychoanalyst
dealing with with surrender
submission and masochism sadomasochism
again should if you find his article
that's online it's like 16 pages or
something not that long of a read a lot
of very valuable information should be
taken with an enormous grain of salt so
one of my main yeah I think the central
thrust of this bit here is that
particularly interfacing you know as we
kind of attempt to find finns in our
postmodern age and i'm using the
metaphor of being submerged in water
very distinctly there we have gone we
have in a sense fallen back on earlier
systems for judging which i i've played
with this in terms of an authenticity
hierarchy as opposed to modernism's
credibility hierarchy and that basically
the major danger or the corruption point
of a authenticity hierarchy is the
ability to basically or rather our lack
of ability to be able to mimic
meaningfully differentiate between a
sense of security and power that comes
from having a deep ontological basis
from portraying and extraordinarily
narcissistic mode of interacting so
basically authenticity hierarchies
corrupt towards narcissism in many ways
like a credibility hierarchy corrupts
towards making it status as opposed to
merit right when they start corrupting
it's because the things like nepotism or
or you know there's many mechanisms but
basically the meritocratic element of a
credibility hierarchy starts losing
ground to something that is the display
of merit without any of the actual meet
of merit so III think this is perhaps
also one element for the the people
interested in the written our thing to
figure out is it would be something like
a mythos that gives people tools to
repeat for being able to differentiate
between people that have ontological
security and people that are
narcissistic and looking at how those
things interact with each other I would
argue that in our in our current system
these are necessary features when you
throw out a strong sense of an objective
truth we we necessarily are going to
start falling back on this and I would
say it's already far too late to try and
make arguments like no throw out all of
social media instead go back to the
institutionalized Sciences as a source
of authority and people right now
especially in a meaning crisis are going
to be looking for people that have
ontological security because it is
synonymous with leading a meaningful
life likewise any religion moving on
from here is going to be able is going
to need to be able to offer that to its
practitioners whether that's one of the
classical religions or someone trying to
create a new way
obviously there are really deep dangers
there and there's gonna be a enormous
potential for people to capitalize on
people's innate sense of narcissism and
abuse and misuse it and be selling them
some sense of ontological security in
the process
while the person is actually not
ontological II secure they're just
evermore narcissistic yeah okay also
I'll be right back my throat is really
dry and I drank all my water good guess
I can plug tomorrow at one o'clock
Eastern mark Vernon's gonna be here
following his voices with rebecky of a
couple weeks ago
for another Q&A so doing this I might I
might also add I think oh sorry I think
this is one of the mechanisms by which
the traditional religions actually
corrupted was mistaking their belief for
a type of narcissistic security right I
am the special person in God's eyes that
type of thing and none of it
particularly giving a legitimate sense
of of deep ontological security and I
might also add that I think part of
ontological security very deeply ties
into for Vicky's definition and use of a
word like a gothic love and this
probably also hinted at although I think
in my opinion not as meaningfully
represented in Buddhist compassion and
things like that and we all kind of know
the story of or the meme if you will
that the person that is most secure in
themselves is often the least excitable
in the sense of having their emotions
manipulated by another and it's usually
those that are trying to put on the air
of ontological security in a
particularly narcissistic fashion that
feels the need to defend themselves from
every meaningless slight against them so
yeah there's differences I'm trying to
highlight here in what those two are and
why people seem so prone to mistake one
sorry I've got a little bit of pushback
on this because I take your point with
rigor with respect to the agape love but
I
Isis but do you agree with the idea that
perhaps John would think that instead of
a copic love intelligibility is the the
source of ontological security let's say
he might I would push back against him
if he did yeah okay yeah I was just
wondering if you could play with those
two ideas the intelligibility plus is
the copic love but I mean it's it's kind
I would I would say that the
intelligibility is playing more deeply
in the credibility hierarchy than it is
in the authenticity hierarchy if I was
to split it into my little system here
right intelligibility would be how you
climb in the credibility hierarchy and
that's also deeply valuable it's just
operating on a different network I think
okay so the the how at the ontological
security tie-in with the credibility and
the sorry what does the other one
authenticity wait are you saying that
those two aren't you don't have a way to
bring those two together I would the the
image I often use here is the Star of
David so you have two hierarchies
balanced against each other and are
mostly overlapping with the very peaks
of each hierarchy as well as the corners
of the bases missing from each other
so in some sense part of the very lowest
of one hierarchy is missing from the
other and the peak is also missing from
the other but I think we need right if
we're describing a stable meaningful
system in some sense it is credibility
that makes authenticity valuable and it
is authenticity that makes credibility
and synthesis right but I'm trying to
connect that to the ontological security
or like I'm just not sure how those
ideas relate right so I would argue that
the the goal of the authenticity
hierarchy is this ontological power yeah
and and you say that that's a gothic
I was trying to point towards a couple
qualities that one might be able to
discern about what ontological security
offers a person that's not present in
narcissism okay
yeah okay I might be trying to be beeped
in with you telling you then sorry
no worries okay so yeah writing a bit
more so dense article the submission
verse surrender I think is also deeply
important because it highlights how
fundamental it is for people to be to
have a deep need for surrender and this
is right why do people interact in the
way they do at all why do we find our
lives becoming increasingly less
meaningful despite the fact that we have
more dominion over the world than ever
before right we we are put ever less in
a position of needing to surrender to
that the things around us right we're
becoming ever closer to the one man is
you know I am an island type mythos
right the peak of individuality or
individuality as ideology and yet we
find ourselves with higher suicide rates
and and you know a crisis of meaning
seemingly as a side effect from this
dent rights and I would agree that there
is well it's almost a type of hegelian
argument that there is some really deep
sense where surrender is where we find
the whole of our being right and this
this has to do with being witnessed it
also has to do with being a witness unto
ourselves you know it's interesting
within Hegel's master-slave dialectic
the master is actually the one in a
weaker ontological position the
because he can never actually know
himself fully because his his self
definition is based off of the slave
that he necessarily is excluded from
whereas the slave can have a full
ontological knowledge of himself because
no part is it is actually excluded it's
not dependent upon the master for his
self definition right if the master
disappears one day it's not like the
slave suddenly has an identity crisis
well they might but they at least have
the potential not to so yes surrender is
one of these mechanisms that's deeply
meaningful especially in say the case of
what verb a key is trying to do by
bringing in transformational systems
you cannot transform without an element
of surrender right it's just not you
must surrender something into something
in order for transformation to occur so
the the deep danger that ghent brings up
is in this mistaking of surrender and
submitting and he kind of pulls the two
apart some of it is a little funky but I
think it's a valuable you know
distinction he's making even if I
disagree with certain aspects one of the
bits is like the use of will right
submit ins is what we do when we
willfully try and surrender right in
some deep sense you can consider
surrender to be similar to the process
of falling asleep it's something that
you can give yourself an affordance for
but you cannot actually will yourself to
sleep likewise you cannot will yourself
into surrender you can only will
yourself into submission
and this is part and this I found very
meaningful coming out of my cult or
going into my cult for experience as I
had just come out of this deep state of
surrender that was extraordinarily
exponentially and ontologically
meaningful and finding myself lacking
that surrender
I immediately willfully sought it in
some sense through submission granted I
did not fully ever submit to the system
but I can see that the the movement
inside my own head for how that
transition occurred and how likely that
transition is to happen so again when
we're talking about meaningful healthy
cultic systems transformational systems
something that makes a very deep
affordance for surrender while being
extraordinarily cautious and present of
the tendency for surrender to slide into
submission is very important within
verbe keys work specifically I've tied
this to the distinction surrender is
what is present in dialo goes right each
peach person is not only right
surrendering to each other but they're
surrendering to the conversation itself
and through that the conversation itself
becomes this transformative practice of
you know of discovery and synthesis the
further you get away from practices like
that and closer towards a classic
student-teacher relationships the more
you're gonna have a much stronger
propensity for that surrender to turn
into submission and with that you're
gonna have a lot of the dangers of you
know classic classic cultic elements
become more present that doesn't mean
that a student-teacher dynamic is going
to be bad it means it has a tremendously
higher chance of forming into a type of
system that Verve a key is perhaps
trying to avoid than through a practice
like dialogue OHS and again you know I
don't think you're gonna get around this
and I ideologies that think that a
person can remain entirely an individual
and being in communion can be in
community I think our our naively
idealistic and also dishonest dishonest
with the person's own phenomenology
that's not to say we can't rationalize
all choices as being individualistic I
just don't think it's it's an honest
look at what's happening as we interact
with the world and more specifically
social structures and anyone want to
push back on on anything I said there
yes do you think that surrender can be
imposed no I think submission can be
imposed absolutely but well okay well
kind of and kind of not right I can
again try and relate my own experience
where I found myself needing to
surrender because surrender was the only
thing that offered relief from the
experience that I was happened having
now could I have not surrendered or was
that surrender imposed on me no not
directly I could have fought against it
I probably just would have ended up
psychotic in the process arguably I
would say to you will necessarily end up
psychotic if you have lost the ability
to surrender much like you would end up
psychotic if you lost the ability to
sleep
shit
so you think you can impose submission
yes absolutely of course
right someone can can overpower you use
a gun break your leg whatever right
the act of submission is still a choice
yeah in some to some degree you know I
mean at a certain point viewing it as a
choice seems more ideologically driven
than meaningfully driven but yes there
is some point where a person could stop
struggling against the situation whether
one calls that surrender or submission
it's perhaps well highly dependent on
the scenario also I don't want to stick
to strong lead against distinction here
again I think there's very many useful
aspects of what he's teasing apart but I
don't want to like view this surrender
vers submission thing as its as it's
like I back it a hundred percent there
are some cases where I think willful
submission can be generative and useful
which he seems very blatantly against
okay
see
yeah so defining oh sorry
cases where surrender and submission
could be generative but generated for
who for the surrender
well there's certainly cases where it's
generative for growth or either party
yeah or or even you know biasing towards
the person submitting is probably fine
we would like it to be more valuable
sorry you know we're getting a quite a
bit of wind I think from you it's not
it's getting hard to hear wind I thought
it was an earthquake earthquake I know
you should probably run for some
yeah so being aware that that some type
of surrender if you're gonna have any
transformation is important
don't be naive and think I can you know
become an entirely different person
without giving anything up
likewise recognizing how extraordinarily
dangerous that is is very important we
got about 20 minutes and I want to make
sure to leave at least 15 or 10 to 15
for questions so I'm gonna speed up a
little bit here and try and hit on what
I consider the more important kind of
safety tools for moving forward so being
deeply aware of narcissistic
transference right a person is way more
likely to fall for the tricks of a
narcissist if they themselves are also a
narcissist likewise being extremely
aware of naivety as a very deep form of
narcissism right truly believing that
you or your thing has the potential to
be exceptional or special or to fix the
problems you should be extraordinarily
skeptical of that and not being
skeptical makes you more likely to fall
for someone who says you know no I
really have figured it out
self-awareness developing self-awareness
getting a clearer understanding of
narcissism how it works and recognizing
its extreme prevalence in our current
situation all of those are very valuable
regardless of whether you're trying to
create a religion or not
[Laughter]
be aware of thought stopping techniques
so in a more general sense going through
Lifton's work and understanding the
mechanisms that he put out for thought
control or thought reform is important
in my first conversation I ran through
the list and also offered ways in which
Lifton's techniques have been updated
you know how you're more likely to
encounter them in our current time that
have it not seemingly been accounted for
elsewhere so I recommend going back to
that I'm not going to run through it
again because it takes quite a bit of
time but I touched on that in the first
conversation let's see graduation so
this is a big one
some of the more healthy overtly
cult-like systems that we have
university being the one that
immediately comes to mind has a
graduation process right so there is
some point where you have learned
everything the system can offer you
within its you know current form and
then you go out and leave the system
behind and you do your own thing ideally
in such a way that it makes the system
that you once belonged to more valuable
in the process of your novel work right
you do not want to find yourself trapped
within a system that never offers any
type of ending point this is how you get
very deeply entrenched power dynamics
and and things like that now that's
gonna struggle quite a bit with some of
the ideas that Verve a Kees been posing
for example when you have this idea that
wisdom is something you must always be
looking for and never find there is no
completion state that likewise makes it
so that any institution giving wisdom is
a permanent institution and you are a
permanent subjugated person within that
system
so you need some way to navigate that
how one goes about doing so is obviously
very difficult and one reason why it's
so much easier to create knowledge
transmission than it is to create wisdom
transmission right you cannot write
wisdom as a as a test where at least
it's very difficult to do so so I don't
I have something to be aware of there
and a mechanism that seems to be healthy
and other systems but I don't have a
good way for transferring it into a
wisdom context ya understand what the
work on brainwashing is context control
how Overton windows work get real clear
on what advertising is how it works a
lot of this is like just learning how to
navigate our current age and becoming
aware of the many ways that we are
subtly manipulated or are put in a state
of submission without our individualist
red flags flying off the handle the next
is a question of boundaries you
generally to oversimplify it massively
have three dominant boundary modes for
cultic structures and these are hard in
easy out easy and easy out and easy in
hard out and with all of these you are
trading off between fending off cultural
entropy entropy and meaningfully and
trading off creating a overly insular
culture that is full of bullshit so what
I found is right the classic easy in
hard out is really creepy do not do that
one it's powerful its effective and it
it almost certainly creates a situation
that is exceptionally open to abuse so
easy and hard out want to avoid that as
much as possible easy in easy out is
what I would say most cultic
affiliations are at right now this is
similar to like okay well I get to
belong to the cultic affiliation of
Volcom by spending $50 on the t-shirt
instead of $10 on the target t-shirt or
whatever right so it cost me 40 bucks
for this association and then I can just
take the shirt off or throw it away and
I no longer hold the Association right
easy and easy out there's not much going
on there the problem comes with dealing
especially you know outside of these
these kind of just stealing when you get
out of just signaling and into
transformative work you're gonna face a
lot of problems with cultural entropy
stripping the meaning and eroding the
meaning from your system and that's
gonna become really prevalent in an easy
and easy out system this is how you get
things like McDonald's yoga right like
where we we we take hatha yoga one of
eight branches of yoga we strip it of
every meaningful context that made it
something sacred and then we sell it to
Westerners as basically you know pseudo
spirit yes
pseudo spiritual Pilates and that's all
there is to it right and yes is it is it
doing something yeah probably
and you know the problem is that if all
of our spiritual or wisdom tradition
tradition systems are functioning on
that principle they will be consumed
alive by the culture and they will never
actually deal with the meaning crisis
problem in any meaningful sense which
leads me to the last which is hard in
easy out you want to form some type of
boundary that makes it relatively hard
for a person to enter into your system
that way they cannot just
steal and run with whatever they want
and go make shitty versions of it
likewise you want to make it as
extremely easy as possible low
commitment to leave and that's actually
really difficult to do for a lot of
other sociological reasons right how
humans form relationships and that type
of stuff but in in my experience this is
how you most this is the best way to
deal with this the the two dangers
appear one becoming creepy and insular
and manipulative and the other being
totally meaningless and ineffective so
and some good you know one good model of
this is something like the Orthodox
Christian Church where it's very easy to
come in you're totally allowed to show
up at a at a whatever a service or a
sermon but to actually be considered a
you know a member of the church is a
very long process of regularly showing
up at that church not having the right
to claim that your forget that
catechumen or whatever that first stages
and and generally showing a lot of
interest and and devotion to wanting to
be part of this structure and it's after
having gone through this and learning
and all this stuff that they finally let
you in so it's not hard in in the sense
of like you can't even get in the door
you want to be able to get in the door
but to be a meaningful contributing
member and to be considered part of the
in-group of the church is quite a to-do
and then of course you can just leave if
you so wish so that's one way to deal
with it many ways to set up this case
but I was just trying to create a broad
broad stroke picture there of different
setups and what the kind of trade-offs
are
Transparency don't do things you'd be
ashamed of this should be obvious and
yet it's usually not in practice you
know this is like the safe space problem
you know you create a little bubble
where you can relax and you know let
down the shields a little and then and
then you find yourself on a slippery
slope towards doing things that you
wouldn't do if you were in more open
view so there are limits to this right
there is a need for private spaces and
private life
however ideally one keeps in mind the
idea of of transparency and not doing
things that we ourselves would be
ashamed of all right we're running out
of time so I'm gonna hit on on the last
one or I've got a bunch more here but
there's one that I think is really
important and very immediately
actionable and that's to create a system
of yellow flags and red flags before you
go into a transformative community or
deal with these types of systems where
you're challenging your worldview at a
very deep level so this is make a list
of yellows this is things that should
give you pause but are not a reason unto
themselves to go fuck this I'm done with
it right yellow flags this should when
you cross one of these it should be
raising your suspicion level it should
be making you really start taking a look
at what's happening and also ideally
kicking in fixes that would be useful to
the group within a healthy group at
least red flags are the no Nevers right
this is like if you run into one of your
predefined red flags you've made a
commitment to yourself to no longer have
anything to do with the group of people
that you're interacting
right and so yellows offer you a little
bit of flexibility and the potential for
growth while allowing you to engage a
defensive system meaningfully red flags
are the is how you keep yourself from
sliding down an endlessly slippery slope
and when it's hard to say this it's it's
it's hard to give people a sense of this
kind of death by a thousand paper cuts
that happens within the these groups but
you know I I credit a good portion of my
leaving cult for with having set up
before interacting with it a list of
signs for myself where I would you know
I drew one line in the sand and then I
drew one in like granite and when I got
up to that line that was carved in
Granite that was how I it's what gave me
the umph to actually be able to kick
myself out of this you know death by a
thousand paper cut slide that I was on
so I really highly recommend doing
something like that when you start
interfacing with you know experimental
groups or or or even not even
experimental groups right they can be
entirely mainstream groups and and you
know the political discourse slides to
such a level that our internal compass
gets totally you know shifted into a
place where we start becoming something
we never thought we could be of course
the much overused reference to Nazi
Germany comes to mind yeah oh okay any
questions sorry I thought I could get
through more of it I got a good number a
good chunk of the good stuff out there
hopefully you guys found some of that
useful and I'm open for Q&A if well just
really quickly the granite line for
caught them before what was it exactly
like what was the thing that kicked you
out of comfortable sorry I was trying to
kick yourself out there heating the
water it was in this case it wasn't even
a the granite line to be honest so much
is like I had not as I had already
experimented with crossing it and it was
in some deep sense watching myself cross
it that gave me a panic attack that
kicked me out of the group in this case
it was a specific form I was given a
slight position of power over one of the
other cult members and it was acting as
a relay between the cult leader and the
person and the mechanisms for growth had
basically started sliding out of a kind
of transformative framework into a
listen to what the cult leader tells you
because it will be faster and more
effective than you figuring it out on
your own and upon relaying a message to
that effect is was my moment where I
crossed the red line and went okay this
is fucked and got the fuck out of there
so I know the warning signs of the
danger of you know where we can go wrong
yeah that's the part I'm the most
interested in do you have enough in what
you didn't get to for maybe a shorter
session where we could really deep dive
into those for like an hour maybe next
week yeah I definitely be down for that
it would probably be a fun one to
actually talk about in a more group like
setting as well where I could list out
some points and some top talking topics
and then get more people involved in the
discussion yes the overt lecture format
here so why don't we squeeze in one yeah
yeah or so yeah one more question from
Ehlo in the Czech I'm gonna read it just
because you know I think you're having
some wind problems do you have specific
comments on behalf I'm sorry do you have
specific comments on being skeptical but
not doubtful and dismissive on the
flipside optimistic but not deluding
yourself yeah I mean you're you're
you're centering in on the problem there
which is just like again
the aspects that we need are the same
ones that make us so susceptible do I
have my you know how to be skeptical
without being doubtful
I mean Brett you could run that way
maybe we could have a little
conversation on that yeah right I mean
it but it is it's it's interesting right
the science of doubt I'm sorry
pleasure of telling science of that you
know you've come from a very skeptic
point and now you're regularly partaking
in rituals and meditation and and all
these things and it seems like you've
afforded yourself a tremendous amount of
pragmatism to be able to make these
moves and explore them by in some sense
judging against your meaning is that
your sense of meaning and there's
there's a difference between skepticism
and being doubtful and being cynical
so there's cynicism which is just more
like the dismissiveness of just you know
that that could never be it you know
pshaw and then there's active open
mindedness
you know not you know being hesitant and
being not willing to just grab on to
whatever gets proposed and wanting you
know a certain standard of evidence but
being open to receiving that and then
there's some pragmatism you know if if
it's you know they're the more dangerous
something is the more the less the the
less I'm willing to just be pragmatic
and and the more I'm going to want it to
be solid before before jumping in when
it's other things were you know the some
experimentation is it was probably not a
bad we could spend I mean yeah maybe we
should we should have a whole discussion
just on
that balance between skepticism and
cynicism and having some amount of tools
for how to stay in it you know how to
navigate that it would probably be very
very useful likewise with the
hopefulness as opposed to the kind of
naive bullshitting of ourselves there's
a reason the major arcana and tarot
starts with the fool and so there is
always some aspect of having to just in
some very real sense be naive enough to
take the step off the cliff and often it
seems more like how do we prevent
needing to do that and more you know how
do i how do I make sure to carry around
the parachute or something you know
something like that so and make that and
that jump more pleasant and less
dangerous we're at eight o'clock why
don't we do one more question for mark
and then maybe the rest of the official
questions at least we couldn't well so
we'll have one more session probably a
little shorter maybe an hour-long
session I guess unless it takes off on
diving into the dangers but mark why
don't you ask your question sorry hey
Nick I had to drop off for a call
unfortunately so I might have missed
this if you if you cover it but Benjamin
Boyce did it recently did a talk with
Paul Andrew clay and Jonathan pezzo and
they covered a wide variety of topics
really interesting talk I know it's been
posted in the in the voice channel text
day a day ago or so and in that one of
the things they were talking about that
really struck me was they were talking
about Obama and how he represented
royalty to some extent and the
relationship between like the
unification of the UK around the royalty
and that interaction with you know it
seems to be like a cultic structure that
interacts with other cultic structures
and so I'm wondering if there's like a
hierarchy of of cultic structures that
interact in some ways
and you know I don't know if you if you
listened to that particular talk but you
know what you thought of that concept in
general where you have you have saved
the state religion right that's that's
that's one cult and then you have the
the monarchy that's another cult that
are operating sort of at the same level
right they in theory at least have the
same amount of power in some sense and
then there's some relationship between
them so I was just I was a comment on
that yeah yeah again I think this gets
into some of the argument I was making
just about how like inevitable the this
qualia of our sociological systems is
and and how deeply it impacts and frames
our phenomenology so yeah you know I
don't know forever gonna create a system
of government where we don't have that
even if it's entirely ran by an AI we
just start viewing the AI as you know
a type of noble godlike creature and
there is something very very deeply I
think important about that role you know
like the idea that the president is
primarily there to make the proper you
know judgment call on policy seems
pretty deeply unrealistic it's it's a
lot of the other systems of our
governments are what are carrying the
weight of that and it seems like the
presidents that we often hold in the
highest regard are those that were able
to meaningfully create a unified dream
about what America represented so when
we listen to JFK's you know speeches or
you know I don't know read Lincoln or
you know these people that were really
powerfully able to create this dream for
America I think it would be a great
mistake to not realize how how extremely
important that is and I think the degree
to which we forget how am
Fortin that is opens the door for more
demagogic
figures to manipulate and make use of
that because we imagine ourselves free
from yeah I don't know that commented on
what you were getting at but yeah I
agree
I mean it is there a hierarchy of hope
that's the religion still interrelate
with the governments and they're both
cults under your structure I believe I
don't I don't I think I understand your
structure pretty well even though I
missed a good chunk of this
unfortunately and so there seemed to be
some relationships that that form
between these cults based on the level
at which they're controlling your your
your ethos or your life I don't I don't
know how to because the right words so I
like is there a hierarchy there is that
or the diversity and think about that I
think there is for the person though
right so a religious persons gonna put
God at the top of a hierarchy and
government is supposed to be a sub
representation principality underneath
God in a secular frame a secularist
might put science up there right and the
government should be purely and only
informed by science and should be
subjugated to whatever science says or
they might be a different type of
secularist
and they put politics up at the top and
science that should be subjugated to
politics in some regard that interplay
has to play out otherwise you don't have
an ethics system for guiding the
investigation of science so right
there's complicated issues there and how
a person hierarchically formats that I
don't know I think we could probably
make an argument that at certain times
through history there's a general
hierarchy that most people accept as the
proper one I don't know if we can fully
encapsulate it in our current age in a
generalized sense so much as in a
personal sense so the person themselves
will hierarchically order their cultic
affiliations
oh wow I didn't yeah I wasn't even
thinking of it from that from that level
in a sense because I fell into what I
now realized as a small trap that I've
been trying to avoid so that's odd so
that's interesting that you did you
frame it that way so is it is it it is
it fair to say that then an unhealthy
cult is an identity collapse into the
cult and that a healthy cult would allow
for other cult identities to exist or
coexist I'd say one of the major
features of a healthy cult is its
ability to consume and interact with
other cults in the same way that what
makes a healthy person is the ability to
eat something other than our own shit
right so when you get isolationist cult
cult soar cultures quite literally if
you map it on to your body right you
you're you are consuming only what you
produce right right you're not consuming
anything from other external sources and
I think this is actually really obvious
when we watch worldviews how they
mimetic aliy move right so for example
one of the reasons I think tosh.o is
such a strong voice right now in the
group that watches him is because he's
constantly interfacing with the world
he's not trying to go all the way back
in time and just say ignore the whole
outside world just believe in the
pre-modern frame he's trying to show you
how the pre-modern frame applies to the
postmodern frame and I consider that an
aspect of what makes a cultic structure
healthy if they have to remember that
one I think so when you've been
consuming what you've been producing I
know it's a great way to say that's
probably a great way to end another
fascinating stream thank you so much
Nick
I mean yeah I feel like we can go on and
on and on and on this there's so much a
lot of material yeah yeah and second
what people said last time I mean yeah
you got to read the book there's so we
will continue this conversation next
week I guess
well we'll finish it up with with part
three and really dive into the the
problems of things to avoid and the less
it really the lessons for us here I mean
that's that's again what's very high in
my mind how do we avoid falling into
these pitfalls you know not just setting
up the yellow and red for what we would
expect from somebody else but what we
would expect from ourselves so you know
so so that'll be fantastic and thank you
so much everyone for being here and
asking just great questions and yeah
what a great this two hours just flew by
thanks so much Nick really appreciate
this yeah yes thank you all for
listening all right have a great night
everyone we'll see you soon